A Guide to the Hawkins Family Papers, 1862-1928
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Hawkins Family Papers, 1862-1928
The Library of Virginia
40620
2.3 cubic feet (6 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased.
Biographical Information
James P. Hawkins was born in Albemarle County, Virginia on 14 January 1845. He lived in Danville, Virginia during the Civil War, where he was an agent for the Southern Express Company. Following the war, Hawkins also became involved in the tobacco industry, becoming a partner in the Roanoke Tobacco Works and Hawkins and Jones. During this time, he also served on the Danville City Council. Hawkins married Philippina Behn McDowell of Charleston, South Carolina on 19 December 1870 in Staunton, Virginia. They had two sons, Richard Montgomery Hawkins (1871-1913) and James P. Hawkins, Jr. (b. 1873). In 1880, Hawkins dissolved his partnership in Hawkins and Jones, and he and his wife moved to Millboro Springs in Bath County, and also had a daughter, Palma Hampton Hawkins (1881-1974). She married James Berlin Dill (1884-1974). James P. Hawkins died on 27 January 1931. Philippina B. Hawkins died on 12 February 1902. They, and their daughter Palma, are buried in the Windy Cove Presbyterian Church cemetery in Millboro Springs.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1862-1928, of the Hawkins family of Bath County, and Danville and Staunton, Virginia, namely James P. Hawkins (1845-1931) and his wife, Philippina Behn (McDowell) Hawkins (1846-1902), and their daughter Palma Hampton Hawkins (1881-1974). The collection contains account books, accounts and receipts, cash book, correspondence, day book, diaries (mainly business matters and farming activities), lumber sales book, memorandum books, photographs, poetry, school exercises, Southern Express tally books, tax tickets and receipts, and tobacco sales records.
The correspondence covering the years 1867-1880 is mainly between James and Philippina while he was living in Danville, Virginia and working as an agent for the Southern Express Company, and she was living in Staunton with his parents, siblings, and their two sons, Richard Montgomery Hawkins (1871-1913) and James P. Hawkins, Jr. (b. 1873). James was also co-partner in the Roanoke Tobacco Works, and later Hawkins and Jones, tobacco dealers and brokers in Danville and Richmond, Virginia. Subjects include business matters, finances, loneliness and separation, health, social events, management and boarding at various hotels, deaths of area residents and fellow boarders, mail deliveries, family news, Philippina's trip to Charleston, South Carolina, and his business travel around the country. The post-1890 letters are mainly from Philippina to her daughter Palma while the latter was attending school at Belmont Seminary in Bedford, Virginia, and later Valley Female Seminary in Waynesboro, and includes advice and inquiries concerning studies, friends, manners, and dress.
Contents List
- Account and Memorandum Books - Southern Express Company, Virginia Central Railroad, 1862-1863. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Account Book, 1865-1867. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Account Book, 1867-1869. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Account Book, 1868-1869. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Account Book, 1871-1874. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Account Book, 1874-1875. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Account Book - Hawkins and Jones, 1876-1878. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1868-1902, 1928. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Accounts and Receipts - R. Chambers and Company, 1874-1877. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bill of Lading. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Business/Calling Cards. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Cash and Account Book,1877-1878, 1887-1891. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cash and Expense Book,1869. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Class Record Book - Palma H. Hawkins. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Compositions. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1858 [1878?]. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1867. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1868. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1870. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1871. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1872. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1873. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1874. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1875. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1876 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1876 (March-August). (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1876 (September-December). (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1877. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1878. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1879. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1880. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1881. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1883. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1884. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1885. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1889. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1890. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1892. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1893. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1895. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1896. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1897. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1898. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1899. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1900. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1901. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1903. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1904. (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1905. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1906. (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
- Daybook and Tobacco Book - Samuel and William Miller, Roanoke Tobacco Works, Danville,1876. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1876. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1877. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1878. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1879. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1883, 1925. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1886. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Diary,1887. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Election Certificates. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Fee Bill. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Lumber Sales Book,1883-1885. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Memorandum Books. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Monteith's Comprehensive Geography. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Poetry. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Promissory Notes. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Quotations and Verse Book. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Rivercomb and Hawkins. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Rowlett's Interest Tables(Sixth Edition),1842. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- School Exercises. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Tally Book - Southern Express Company, Danville,1867. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Tax Tickets and Receipts. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Tobacco Accounts and Sales. (Box 4, Folder 12)